Guide to the Edward H. Chamberlin papers, 1896-2017 and undated RL.11776
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1920-1966 and undated; 1
  - Tinbergen, Jan, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence reminiscing about time Tinbergen spent in Cambridge, MA, as well as a letter about Tinbergen
  - Ting, Chen, 1945-1949 (Box 2)
  - Tintner, Gerhard, 1934-1937 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about exchanging papers and arranging communication over the phone
  - Tobin, James, 1938-1939 (Box 2)
    Includes routine correspondence about Chamberlin supporting Tobin for fellowships
  - Triffin, Robert, 1938-1949 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about monopolistic competition and general equilibrium, as well as other routine correspondence
  - Ulman, Lloyd, 1943 (Box 2)
  - V, 1933-1964 (Box 2)
  - Van Winkle, Martha, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Vanek, Jaroslav, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about Vanek's books being submitted to Harvard University Press and his departure from Harvard for Cornell
  - Vietnam, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence and other materials about the economic situation in Vietnam
  - Viner, Jacob, 1930-1962 (Box 2)
  - W, 1930-1959 (Box 3)
  - Walker, Gilbert, 1934 and undated (Box 3)
  - Walker, Mabel, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Walker, Ronald, 1935-1937 (Box 3)
  - Wallace, Don, 1934-1939 (Box 3)
  - Ward, Patrick J., 1950 (Box 3)
  - Watkins, Ralph J., 1960 (Box 3)
  - Watson, Edward P., 1949 (Box 3)
  - Waugh, Frederick, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Weintraub, Sidney, 1950 (Box 3)
    Includes routine correspondence about receipt of a paper
  - White, Horace Jr., 1936-1938 (Box 3)
  - White, Wilford, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Wilcox, Clair, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Williamson, K. M., 1936 (Box 3)
  - Williamson, Oliver, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Wilson, Charles Erwin, 1946 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence with president of General Motors about negotiating with United Autoworkers Union for wage decreases to help lower prices
  - Wilson, Norman, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Yatrou, Michael, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Yohr, W. A., 1949 (Box 3)
  - Young, H. G., 1925 (Box 3)
  - Zeller, Bruno, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Zolotas, Xenophon, 1962 (Box 3)
- Conferences and Organizations, 1933-1985 and undated; 2
  This series documents Chamberlin's speaking engagements at conferences and workshops, his roles in professional organizations, and his expert testimony before United States Congressional committees. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Albion College, 1958 (Box 3)
    Includes materials related to Chamberlin's participation in a Social Science Conference hosted at Albion.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1942-1964 (Box 3)
    Includes materials related to Chamberlin's membership in the Academy
  - American Council on Education, 1947-1960 (Box 3)
    Includes documents related to international scholars hosted at Harvard University and Chamberlin's role in the program
  - American Economic Association (AEA), 1933-1964; 4 folders (Box 3)
    Includes documents related to Chamberlin's involvement on the Association's nominating committee and committee on economists' public service, as well as materials for annual conferences, correspondence with J. M. Clark about organizing conference sessions, and roundtable on monopolistic competition
  - American Enterprise Institute, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to the distribution of Institute publications authored by Chamberlin
  - American Institute of France, 1947 (Box 3)
    Includes meeting minutes of the advisory committee
  - American Mining Congress, 1962 (Box 3)
    Includes materials related to speaking engagement on labor unions
  - Arden House, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    Includes materials from conference on Appraisal of the Market Models of Price Theory hosted at Columbia University
  - Buffalo Chamber of Commerce, 1948 (Box 3)
    Includes notes for talk given
  - Case Institute, 1960-1964; 5 folders (Box 3)
    Includes materials related to Chamberlin's participation in an Economics-in-Action seminar series
  - Catholic Economic Association, 1949-1962 (Box 3)
    Includes documents related to membership in the association
  - Catholic Commission on Intellectual and Cultural Affairs, 1947-1964 (Box 3)
    Includes newsletters and directories
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, undated (Box 3)
  - Cement Testimony, 1940 (Box 3)
    Includes copy of Chamberlin's testimony on pricing and competition in the cement industry
  - Claremont, 1953 (Box 3)
    Includes materials related to speaking engagement
  - Committee on Research in the Social Sciences, 1934 (Box 3)
    Includes documents related to committee research on French railways
  - Conference Notes, undated (Box 3)
    Includes notes on presentations from unspecified conference
  - Council of Economic Advisers, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    Includes travel documents and background material related to Chamberlin's participation in the council
  - Du Pont, 1950 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence related to Chamberlin's attendance at meetings hosted by Du Pont
  - Dunster House Talk on Minimum Wages, 1937 (Box 4)
  - ECA Mission to France, 1941-1959 (Box 4)
    Includes materials related to international exchange of scholarly research with France
  - Economic Club of Detroit, 1959 (Box 4)
    Includes luncheon program
  - Eliot House, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Engagements, 1959 (Box 4)
    Includes materials from various speaking engagements
  - England, 1959 (Box 4)
    Includes materials related to scheduling various speaking engagements during a trip to England
  - Festschrift for Chamberlin and Library Fund, 1965-1985 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to conference in honor of Chamberlin and fund for library book purchases
  - Ford Foundation, 1957 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence about scheduling a lecture
  - France, 1959 (Box 4)
    Includes materials related to scheduling speaking engagements during trip to France
  - France - Notes, 1950 (Box 4)
    Includes notes related to trip to France
  - French Correspondence - Introductions, 1951-1954 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to French scholars' visit to Harvard
  - Fullbright, 1949-1951 (Box 4)
    Includes documents from Chamberlin's participation in the Fulbright Commission and visits to French universities
  - Georgetown, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Economics Club, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Greece, 1959 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to scheduling trip to Greece and visits to Greek universities
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1957-1965 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to fellowship
  - Harvard Club, Concord, undated (Box 4)
  - International Economic Association (IEA), 1950-1959; 5 folders (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to conference presentations and roundtable on inflation
  - Italy, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to scheduling trip to Italy and visits to Italian universities
  - Joint Committee on the Economic Report, 1947 (Box 4)
    Includes Chamberlin's responses to questionnaire sent to prominent economists by congressional committee
  - Lecture Trip - France, 1950-1954 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to lecture schedule on visit to France
  - Lecture Trip - Outside France, 1950-1951 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to lecture schedule in European countries other than France
  - Marketing Seminar - Burlington (University of Vermont), 1954 (Box 4)
  - Mexico, undated (Box 4)
    Includes travel documents
  - Middlebury Cultural Conference, 1946 (Box 4)
    Includes program and related correspondence
  - Mont Pelerin Society, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to annual meetings and announcements to members
  - National Association of Manufacturers, 1963 (Box 4)
    Includes declined invitation
  - National Recovery Administration, 1934 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence related to Chamberlin potentially serving on Consumers' Advisory Board
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1963 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to membership
  - Norway - Sweden, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to travel to Norway and Sweden
  - Paris Lectures, 1950 (Box 4)
    Includes lecture materials
  - Pittsburgh, 1954 (Box 4)
    Includes materials related to teaching summer session at the University of Pittsburgh
  - Relm Foundation, 1956-1963 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to grant-funded research
  - Royal Economic Society, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Seminar at Catholic University of Milan, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Seminary of Our Lady of Providence, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, 1958 (Box 4)
    Includes copy of testimony given by Chamberlin
  - Social Action Institute, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Southern Methodist University (Homan - Texas), 1963-1963 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to speaking engagement
  - Spanish Academy, 1958-1967 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to honorary membership
  - Stanford University, 1936 (Box 4)
    Includes declined invitation to teach during the summer
  - State Department, 1950 (Box 4)
    Includes documents related to Chamberlin's service as a Lecturer for the Foreign Service Institute
  - Talk to Post-War Group of Students, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Talloires, 1951 (Box 5)
    Includes conference program and other related materials
  - Tavern Club, 1940 (Box 5)
    Includes copy of speech given
  - Trade Regulation Law Journal, 1950 (Box 5)
    Includes invitation to be on journal advisory board
  - Travel North, 1950-1951, 1959 (Box 5)
    Includes correspondence related to travel arrangements to Scandinavian countries and Switzerland
  - University of California, 1936-1963 (Box 5)
    Includes declined invitations to teach during summer session
  - University of Massachusetts and Clark University, 1958 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan, 1955 (Box 5)
    Includes documents for travel arrangements for speaking engagement
  - University of Southern California, 1950 (Box 5)
    Includes declined invitation to teach during summer session
- Writings, 1922-1967 and undated; 3
  This series contains copies, reprints, drafts, notes, and other documents associated with Chamberiln's scholarly and popular writings and his service as an editor. These include: reprints and copies of published journal articles and book chapters; draft writings; reviews of published work by Chamberlin and others; copies of books written by Chamberlin; and files from Chamberlin's activity as an editor.
  - Articles, Book Chapters, and Other Papers, 1922-1964 and undated; 1
    This subseries includes reprints, copies, drafts, and other related materials for Chamberlin's scholarly writings in academic journals, edited volumes, and other outlets; also included are writings for popular media. Files are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - A Comparison Between Monopolistic and Imperfect Competition, 1936 (Box 5)
      Draft
    - Advertising Costs and Equilibrium - A Correction, 1944-1945 (Box 5)
      Reprint
    - Advertising Costs and Equilibrium - A Rejoinder, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - An Experimental Imperfect Market, undated (Box 5)
      Reprint and draft
    - Approaches to Dealing with Wage-Push Inflation, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Can Union Power Be Curbed, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Capacita d'Acquisto, 1935 (Box 5)
      Copy of book chapter contributed to edited volume published in Italian
    - Comment on de Jong Manuscript, undated (Box 5)
      Includes comments on a draft
    - Comment on Fouraker, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Comment on Lewis, "Economics by Admonition", 1959 (Box 5)
    - Comment on Wright, "Associations, Morals and Growth, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Consumer Services of the Federal Government, 1934 (Box 5)
      Reprint and draft of report issued by US government
    - Consumers' Clubs, Councils, etc, undated (Box 5)
    - Definition of Selling Costs, 1959-1964 (Box 5)
      Drafts, proofs, and reprint
    - Discussion of Paper by Arthur R. Burns, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Discussion on Power Blocs and the Operation of Economic Forces (papers by Lewis and Hildebrand), 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - Discussion of "Production Heterogeneity and Public Policy", 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - Draft Writing on Inflation, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Duopoly: Value Where Sellers are Few, 1929 (Box 5)
      Proofs
    - Early Development of Monopolistic Competition Theory, undated (Box 5)
    - Economic Analysis of Labor Union Power, 1957-1958; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Drafts, reprint, and related correspondence
    - Elasticities, Cross-Elasticities, and Market Relationships - Comment, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Ends, Indifference and Competition, 1938 (Box 5)
    - Excess Capacity, 1960-1964 and undated (Box 5)
      Drafts and reprint of Italian translation
    - Foreword, 1954 (Box 5)
      Draft foreword for unspecific piece of writing
    - France Gave Too Much Too Soon, 1943 (Box 5)
      Draft, copy, and related correspondence for newspaper piece
    - Full Cost and Monopolistic Competition, 1952 (Box 5)
    - Impact of Recent Monopoly Theory on the Schumpeterian System, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Labor Power and Restraint, 1963 (Box 5)
      Proofs and related correspondence for contribution to the Conservative Papers edited by Congressperson Melvin Laird
    - Labor Union Power, 1962 (Box 5)
      Copies
    - Labor Union Power and Cost-Inflation, 1959 and undated (Box 5)
      Drafts
    - Labor Union Power and the Public Interest, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
      Draft and reprint
    - Labor Union Power: What Can We Do About It, 1959-1962 (Box 5)
      Drafts and reprint
    - Measuring the Degree of Monopoly and Competition, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Men and Machines, 1937 (Box 5)
    - Monopolistic or Imperfect Competition, 1937-1938 (Box 5)
      Reprints of paper and comments by others on the paper
    - Monopolistic Competition Revisited, 1951 (Box 5)
      Includes reprints in English, French, and Italian
    - Moral Issues of Concentrated Economic Power, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Nature of Equilibrium in Monopolistic Competition, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Nature of Equilibrium in Monopolistic Competition - Reply to Demsetz, 1964; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Reprint and copy
    - New York Times: Letters to the Editor, 1945-1958 (Box 5)
      Drafts and copies of various letters to the editor
    - Non-Price Competition, 1951 (Box 5)
      Working paper
    - Numbers and Elasticities, undated (Box 5)
    - On the Origin of Oligopoly, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Origin and Early Development of Monopolistic Competition Theory, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Product As An Economic Variable, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Product Heterogeneity and Public Policy, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Profits, Wages and Price Levels, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Proportionality, Divisibility and Economies of Scale, 1948 and undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Reply to Nichol, "Professor Chamberlin's Theory of Limited Competition", 1934 (Box 6)
    - Report of Committee on Economists in the Public Service, 1946 (Box 6)
    - Review of Knight, "The Ethics of Competition, and Other Essays", 1937 (Box 6)
    - Review of Lyon, "The Economics of Free Deals", undated (Box 6)
    - Review of Mason, "The Street Railway in Massachusetts", undated (Box 6)
    - Review of Pegrum, "Rate Theories and the California Railroad Commission", undated (Box 6)
    - Review of Stigler, "The Theory of Price", 1947 (Box 6)
      Draft, reprint, and notes
    - Reviews of Other Economists' Work, 1942-1959 and undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
      Includes draft reviews of work by multiple economists
    - Schumpeter Britannica Entry, 1958 (Box 6)
      Draft entry on Joseph Schumpeter for the Encyclopedia Britannica
    - Selling Costs, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Some Aspects of Non-Price Competition, 1951-1953 (Box 6)
    - Some Aspects of Railroad Rates, 1922 (Box 6)
      Draft Master's thesis from University of Michigan
    - Some Differences Between Monopolistic and Imperfect Competition, undated (Box 6)
    - Tentative Suggestions on Anti-Trust Policy, 1936 (Box 6)
    - Una Nuova Formulazione della Teoria della Concorrenza Monopolistica, 1954 (Box 6)
      Reprint in Italian
    - United Nations: France, undated (Box 6)
    - Unlabeled Papers, 1948 and undated (Box 6)
      Drafts of untitled papers
    - Various Views on the Monopoly Problem, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Books, 1933-1967 and undated; 2
    This subseries includes copies of different editions and translations of Chamberlin's published books, as well as related correspondence and reviews. Files are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Monopolistic Competition Theory: Studies in Impact, 1967 (Box 8)
      Wiley and Sons, Inc., festschrift in honor of Chamberlin
    - Monopoly and Competition and Their Regulation, 1954 (Box 8)
      Macmillan and Co., volume edited by Chamberlin
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (1st edition), 1933 (Box 7)
      Harvard University Press
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (2nd edition), 1936 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (3rd edition), 1938 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (3rd edition, 2nd printing), 1939 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (5th edition), 1946 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (5th edition, 3rd printing), 1947 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (6th edition), 1948 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (6th edition, 2nd printing), 1950 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (7th edition), 1956 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (7th edition, 2nd printing), 1958 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (7th edition, 3rd printing), 1960 (Box 7)
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (French translation), 1953 (Box 7)
      Presses Universitaires de France
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (Italian translation), 1961 (Box 7)
      University of Florence
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (Japanese translation), 1966 (Box 7)
      Charles E. Tuttle, Co., Tokyo
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (Russian translation), 1959 (Box 7)
      Moscow
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (Spanish translation), 1963 (Box 7)
      Fondo de Cultura Economica, Mexico; pages unopened
    - Towards A More General Theory of Value, 1957 (Box 8)
      Oxford University Press
    - Towards A More General Theory of Value, 1957 (Box 8)
      Greenwood Press, Publishers
    - Towards A More General Theory of Value (Italian translation), 1960 (Box 8)
      Turin; includes partial dust jacket
    - Towards A More General Theory of Value (Italian translation), 1960 (Box 8)
      Turin
    - Dust Jackets, undated (Box 6)
      Includes partial dust jackets from some of Chamberlin's books
    - Impact of the Union, 1950-1951 (Box 6)
      Includes draft transcript of discussion between Chamberlin, Frank Knight, Milton Friedman, Gottfried Haberler, Kenneth Boulding, Paul Samuelson, and others for publication in edited volume
    - Monopoly and Competition and Their Regulation, 1953-1965; 2 folders (Box 6)
      Includes unbound galley proofs and reviews
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition (French translation), 1952 (Box 6)
      Includes galley proofs corrected by Chamberlin that were never received by the publisher
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition - Reviews, 1934-1962; 2 folders (Box 6)
      Includes reviews about Chamberlin's book
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition - Royalties, 1956-1964 (Box 6)
      Includes correspondence related to book orders and royalties
    - Theory of Monopolistic Competition After Thirty Years, 1966 and undated (Box 6)
      Includes drafts for volume appraising The Theory of Monopolistic Competition
    - Towards a More General Theory of Value, 1953-1957 (Box 6)
      Includes correspondence about publishing contract and book sales
  - Editorships and Other Writings, 1936-1961; 3
    This subseries includes files from Chamberlin's activities as an editor and other writings. Files are arranged alphabetically by name.
    - Fortune, 1937-1950 (Box 6)
      Includes documents related to pieces on Chamberlin
    - Harvard University Press, 1936-1961 (Box 6)
      Includes documents related to translations of books
    - Macmillan Company, 1938 (Box 6)
      Includes report on book submitted for publication
    - McGraw- Hill: Harvard Economics Handbooks Series, 1938-1961 (Box 6)
      Includes correspondence and other materials related to establishing handbook series
    - Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1948-1961 (Box 6)
      Includes correspondence and other documents related to Chamberlin's editorship of the journal
    - Review of Economic Studies, 1945-1950 (Box 6)
      Includes documents related to submitting articles and journal subscription
- Research and Notes, 1915-1975 and undated; 4
  This series includes materials from Chamberlin's research. Files include notes, readings on specific subjects of interest to Chamberlin, and writings by others used in research. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Research, 1915-1963 and undated; 1
    This subseries includes notes and readings used in Chamberlin's research. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Beyond Firm, 1949-1963 (Box 9)
      Includes readings and research materials on industry- and sector-wide wage bargaining
    - Collective Bargaining, 1947-1960; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Demand for Labor, 1950-1955 (Box 9)
    - Employment, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Exploitation, 1950 (Box 9)
    - Frictions - Non-competing Groups, 1952-1960 (Box 9)
      Includes readings on labor market frictions
    - Full Cost- Ex Capacity, 1949-1954 (Box 9)
      Includes notes on full cost pricing and excess capacity
    - Group, Cross-Elasticity, 1942-1958 (Box 9)
      Includes notes on elasticity
    - Inflation, 1951-1961; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Internal Organization, 1943-1959 (Box 9)
      Includes notes and readings on firms' internal organization
    - Labor Unions, 1956-1963; 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Monopolistic Competition, 1949 (Box 10)
    - Non-Wage, 1958-1960 (Box 10)
      Includes readings and notes on non-wage benefits
    - Notes on Kaldor, Robinson, and Monopolistic Competition, undated (Box 10)
      Includes notes on writings about monopolistic and imperfect competition by Nicholas Kaldor and Joan Robinson
    - Oligopoly, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 10)
    - Policy, 1957-1960 (Box 10)
      Includes notes and readings on labor and anti-trust policy
    - Productivity, 1945-1962 (Box 10)
    - Progress - Automation, 1955-1961 (Box 10)
    - Reference Index, 1915-1960 and undated (Box 23)
      Includes notecards containing bibliographic information for sources and notes on topics used in Chamberlin's research.
    - Right to Work, 1953-1960; 2 folders (Box 10)
      Includes notes and readings on right to work laws
    - Selling Costs, 1962 and undated (Box 10)
      Includes notes and readings on firms' pricing practices
    - Sharing, Quasi-Rents, 1947-1961 (Box 10)
      Includes notes and readings on wage bargaining, unions, and management practices
    - Union Power, undated (Box 10)
  - Writings by Others, 1925-1975 and undated; 2
    This subseries includes select scholarly and popular writings by others used as reference materials in Chamberlin's research. Files are arranged alphabetically by category, preserving original arrangement.
    - Cost, 1930-1958; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Economic Journal, 1932-1958 (Box 10)
      Includes copies of journal issues
    - Economic Journal, 1942-1950 (Box 11)
    - Individuals, 1927-1958; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Includes reprints of biographical articles about economists
    - Industrial Policy, 1934-1960; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - International Trade, 1949-1961; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Macro, Development, Keynes, 1935-1961; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Marketing and Spatial Competition, 1930-1975; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Money Cycles, 1927-1963; 2 folders (Box 12)